Mate, you are often referring that we should go back to the sūtas, actually, what is written in the sūtas.
Is that kind of... is that your personal approach, or there is, how should I say, a school, should I call it, within saṅgha, within big
Right.
Well, I think it's just a question of label, you know.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm sure there are a few more monks that would agree with me in terms of going back to the suttas and not trusting the later Abhidhamma in commentaries.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I wouldn't say there is a school of us that we got together and decided that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's more like just individuals on the base of their practice, so that that makes more sense, and it's least risky.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also, so that, like, you know, the latest stuff, it's often contradicting what the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_00]: And therefore, you can't trust it.
In regard...
To what is said now, can you give us some advice on how to do metta bhāvanā, how to do metta meditation?
Because it seems to me that it is very related, what you mentioned, to accept everything as it is and, you know, how to say to
to regard to everything what is happening to us with a kind of positive attitude.
[SPEAKER_03]: However, during usual description of metta meditation, very often it's said that we
[SPEAKER_03]: We're supposed to develop some kind of love or positive emotions towards, you know, our surroundings and everything what is happening.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it seems to me that it should be more like you mentioned before, just to be open and to accept everything what is happening.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, I would really appreciate if you could say a few words about the Metta meditation.
[SPEAKER_03]: And especially, I'm interested, would you recommend to do, like, all four stages, or all four kinds, like metta, mudita, etc.?
?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, first, that's what you described as commonly... metta, as commonly taught, is not metta, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: You read the suttas, there is no spreading of love and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's spreading of non-ill-will.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there's no spreading either.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's more like expanding your mind, so to include everything else, so there is no basis for ill-will.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when the mind is expanded in a sense that it cannot resist anything, good or bad, there is no basis for hatred to arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the necessary basis for manifestation of any particular hatred is resistance, is refusal to accept it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If the mind is so expanded that it cannot resist anything anymore, it cannot resist this body, other bodies, in any direction of the world, then there is no basis for hatred and that's the pure metta, non-ill-will.
[SPEAKER_00]: As I say often, opposite... love is not opposite of ill-will.
[SPEAKER_00]: Love is opposite of non-love.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ill-will is opposite of non-ill-will.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, if you practice metta, you will abandon both love and ill-will.
[SPEAKER_00]: And as for the four stages, they're not four stages.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's one practice that you can take on, like, higher levels.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there are four of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you start developing the first metta.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through that, you will develop second.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through that, you will develop third.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through that, you can develop fourth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just like jhānas.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't do one, two, three, four, but it's within establishing yourself in first jhāna, you then get to develop the second one.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, within developing metta, you then get to develop karuṇa, upeka, eventually, in the end.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not a matter of choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hey, let me develop upeka and equanimity now.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's impossible, because the mind is affected by your will and everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's how, if you want metta to do it in non-abstract sense,
[SPEAKER_00]: You just have to stop resisting yourself here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Feelings that you have, perceptions that you have, stop acting towards pleasant ones and stop resisting the uncomfortable ones.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's always why every metta starts with yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not by spreading love to yourself, but by developing non-resistance in regard to yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you don't resist these five senses, if you don't act out of these five senses, you cannot resist or act out towards anything that comes on account of them, that is second to them, which is other people in the world.
[SPEAKER_03]: Pante, what do you think about this vipassana which is taught by Goenka group?
[SPEAKER_03]: What would be your comment on this practice?
I'm interested.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a... it's a wrong... a wrong direction of the effort, because it's based... it's a practice that's based on observation of things, observation of your senses, observation of sensations, which are basically bodily touches, internal or external.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not based on understanding of the context, understanding of your intentions, understanding of the state of mind, because you expect just things to be shown to you through observation, not through effort to understand.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's ultimately a different direction from where the dhamma is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why when Buddha said, when he described, for example, walking meditation, he didn't say you walk by feeling the soles of your feet and knees bending and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said, walking up and down, I purify my mind from unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the instruction.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the unwholesome state?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, lust is unwholesome state, greed is unwholesome state, jealousy is unwholesome state, envy, ill will, irritation, hatred, all of those are unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what vipassana does on account of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's watch sensations, so that they will magically dispel our unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: I am the one responsible for unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you do the walking or sitting, because it's a repetitive or still action, so it doesn't take too much of your attention to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you need all of your attention and focus in a sense of context and mindfulness towards recognizing the mental states that are there, that you are subjected under.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there is no technique for that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just effort based on the instruction and correct information that sends you that way and tells you that's what you need to look for.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, but when you are sitting enough, long enough, and observing such sensations, then, as a result of it, you can also learn a lot of your mind, how it works, about your motivations, about resistance, about everything what you are talking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you learn that because I told you that's what you need to learn.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you were to start, for example, if vipassana is truly vipassana, you wouldn't need all of this I'm telling you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You would simply watch your sensations and arrive at the same conclusions.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you don't.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only reason you arrive at the conclusions of, I need to see my intention, I need to understand this, I need to practice sense restraint, is because somebody told you you need to do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you don't need to watch your sensations for the sake of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just need to not forget what you have to do that you already know.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you want to sit quietly or walk up and down, do so contemplating what you need to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: You must... and Buddha says what you need to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said you should not tolerate thoughts of sensuality, thoughts of ill will, thoughts of hatred.
[SPEAKER_00]: You should not welcome, entertain, encourage them to stay longer.
[SPEAKER_00]: You should not act out of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what you need to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just when people see... they already know this from the suttas and from the instruction, then they do this sensation watching or whatever else, that kind of results in calmness or whatever else, which is fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same like, you know, lay down and relax if you are tense.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a valid experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: But because, you know, you were taught that there is much more to it, you end up ascribing all these values, such as, you know, seeing my motivation, intention, to that vipassana practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has nothing to do with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only reason you know that the mental states of ill-will is... are bad, is because you were told they were bad, you thought about it, you saw for yourself that they are bad, and they'll cause you suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sensation watching had nothing to do with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you still are doubtful about it, as I said, take the experiment of somebody who hasn't been told about the value of virtue, sensory strength, and mindfulness, and give them the sensation watching.
[SPEAKER_00]: Will they arrive at the same values?
[SPEAKER_00]: Not a chance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not in a million years.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because watching sensation is nothing other than watching bodily touches, or listening to the sounds of the ear.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, keeping the mind on the level of the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not on the level of the nature behind the senses that you need to understand.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it doesn't matter how you breathe, how you walk.
[SPEAKER_00]: What matters is to be aware of the mental states in regard to your breathing, in regard to your walking.
[SPEAKER_00]: Are they wholesome?
[SPEAKER_00]: Are they unwholesome?
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I welcoming them?
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I delighting in them?
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I ignoring them?
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I fearing them?
[SPEAKER_00]: And so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's the work.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the true vipassana.
[SPEAKER_00]: Understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if it were, if the wisdom were on the level of the senses, the Buddha would have said so.
[SPEAKER_00]: He would say, just sit down feeling the sensations in your body and wisdom will arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said, sit down and understand the nature of the body within your body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Understand the nature of feelings within your feelings, the nature of mind within your mind, the nature of thoughts within your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: How do you understand?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, for example, by contemplating death in regard to the body, by contemplating a subject to change in regard to the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you practice mindfulness of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you do the vipassana of the mind,
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't watch the sensations of moment-to-moment passing awareness or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: He says, you know mind affected with lust as mind affected with lust.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you endure it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't act out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't delight in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't welcome it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He knows mind affected with anger as mind affected with anger.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then he watches the physical.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then he doesn't lose the sight of the mind affected with anger until that anger disappears.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, he spent the time enduring the angry mind without acting out of that angry mind, and without welcoming, delighting in it, entertaining it, prolonging it, making it worse.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you train that internal immovability in regard to the states of mind, feeling, and the positions of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in that sense, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's completely the opposite direction from the direction of sense observation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Feeling, touching, looking, sensing, hearing, and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: Would you say that this is, this is though, could be an introduction, introductory state?
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Start meditating.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Introduction is learning about the precepts, sense restraint, value of seclusion, mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's your introduction.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's not what I meant.
[SPEAKER_02]: When you sit, and you try to, well, Buddha says that the bhikkhu enters and dwells in
[SPEAKER_02]: The first jhāna, etc.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, maybe this would be like a way, just a method, to calm the mind down, to bring it back.
[SPEAKER_00]: What would be the method to calm the mind down?
[SPEAKER_02]: To watch the sensations.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's because that's not what the mind is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why would watching the sense touches of your body?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, just for the first couple of minutes, maybe.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, again, like, yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you need to calm down, if you need to calm down, if you were sort of busy or agitated, yeah, calm down.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not how vipassana is advertised, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't say, oh, this is a mere relaxation technique for which, you know, have a back massage, lay down, sleep a bit, wake up, relax, go for a walk, and then start doing the work.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's advertised as the work.
[SPEAKER_00]: Watching sensation leads to enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's simply not the case.
[SPEAKER_01]: I had a follow-up question.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bhante, how would you characterize the distinction between a. a sensation, being aware of sensations, then b. contemplation, as reflective awareness, mindfulness, as you describe it, and c. intellection, regular thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: What would be helpful ways of thinking about these three phenomena or processes?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, sensation is basically... you need to undo all the mistaken views.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sensation is almost regarded as if it's a sort of feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: But sensation, in reality, is just a physical sense of touch experienced internally.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why it's always measured as, oh, I'm feeling it in my knees, or my back, or my belly, and it feels like this, feels like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't feel.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're perceiving it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's a mere sense of touch.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you sit on a chair, you have a sensation where you're leaning on the chair.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, if there is sensation of ants in my arms, for whatever reason, whether I pin the nerve or something, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: The point is, sensations are on the level of sight, sound, smell, taste, touches.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is nothing more to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are... there is no special property of sensations that somehow magically reveals you the truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: What was the second one?
[SPEAKER_01]: Reflective awareness and mindfulness, as you describe it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, the third was intellectual.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, well, let me start with the third one.
[SPEAKER_00]: Third one is the intellect.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's using your own reasoning, like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: You realize, wait a minute, these things that I read today, that say Buddhist meditation is, I don't find in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the Buddha and the meditation that's mentioned in the suttas does not quite match the meditation you read about today.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you use your reason to recognize that there is a problem there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't have it both ways.
[SPEAKER_00]: If they are not saying the same thing, well, only one of them is then right.
[SPEAKER_00]: They can't be both right.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you use your intellect to discern where the quality of information, let's say like that, the accuracy of the information you're collecting about the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, the second one, the contemplation that reflects awareness, is exactly that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, seeing it in practice, seeing it in your life, seeing it in your states of mind, not mere theory.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, really, Buddhist meditation should be Buddhist contemplation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the idea of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Mind you, meditation, even in Christianity, means that, means recollecting, you know, thinking about the God, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But today, when you say meditation, means concentrating, focusing, until I'm unaware of everything else, and I'm one-pointed, where nothing else exists.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I said that many times, that the Buddha himself described that in the suttas as a completely wrong meditation, that he compared to, like, an animal, sort of, waiting for a cat, waiting for a mouse to pounce it on.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's so concentrated, the whole world disappears, just sees one thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's completely the mīccha samādhi, the wrong direction of your samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, contemplation will basically
[SPEAKER_00]: Make you think rightly and discern that right direction I'm talking about, on the basis of rightly selected information.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you were... if you heard wrongly, you will not be able to arrive at the right conclusions, because you don't have the right instruction and right pointers.
[SPEAKER_02]: How would you describe right samādhi?
[SPEAKER_02]: You just mentioned wrong samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, right samādhi is that, purifying your mind from the unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when the lust is present, for example, not welcoming it, not acting out of it, not trying to get rid of it, not trying to explain it, or justify it, or avoid responsibility for it, enduring it rightly, is the right samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you learn how to endure things without acting out of it, you are practicing samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly what the Buddha described in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said samādhi is when things try to move the monk's mind, but the monk's mind doesn't move, on account of things trying to move it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how he developed samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: He didn't say samādhi is when he gets so focused on his nostrils, the whole world disappears.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's immovability in regard to things that want to move you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, see, you are already practicing samādhi in a day-to-day life, whether you want it or not, because you are already forced to endure things whether you want it or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem is, without the right instructions, you will not necessarily learn on account of that endurance.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you know, as I said, how to endure things on that right level, that will result in that irreversible wisdom.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I thought the fourth jhāna was synonymous with right
[SPEAKER_00]: No, the first jhāna is already synonymous with right samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: But see, what is the... First of all, that right concentration means right samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's just that whoever translated that chose the word concentration.
[SPEAKER_00]: We choose composure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, right composure is the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, the first jhāna is the measure of your correct samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there are, you know, quite a bit of development before the first jhāna that goes in the direction of right samādhi, but it doesn't quite constitute the first jhāna yet.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because for Sotāpanna, he doesn't need to have jhāna to get the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he does need to grasp the signs of his mind, as we spoke before.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is a necessary prerequisite for developing the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there is no right samādhi without the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, gaining the right view means Sotāpanna already has a form of right samādhi, although he's not quite on the level of jhāna yet.
We often talk about this activity of preparing to some situations.
[SPEAKER_04]: But sometimes, as I observe my life and my inner processes and so on, happening at the moment, often
[SPEAKER_04]: You are surprised by the complexity and by the magnitude of some emotions that appear and that you are not aware that they will appear.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you can't prepare to them.
[SPEAKER_04]: And I can observe at this particular case, when some
[SPEAKER_04]: Life or some processes are coming to an end.
[SPEAKER_04]: And as close as you are to an end, there comes, in my case, a big, big, big bag of guilt.
[SPEAKER_04]: And how can you prepare and how do you deal with this big magnitude of emotions, when you feel that you have missed before and now
[SPEAKER_00]: You are only there with a big guilt and this is... you have to deal with... Well, that's... that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to start dealing with smaller emotions of a smaller magnitude before they get that big.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can't... it doesn't get that big on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: It gets that big because you've been ignoring all the small signs and tokens that are pointing that it's gonna get that big.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you have been ignoring and now you're facing a big guilt, well, the first thing you have to do is not act out of it and endure it until it ceases.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, learn your lesson from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: In a sense that, remember now how big that guilt was and how unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, next time, don't wait that long.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't let it get that much out of hand.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because sometimes, if you ignore and you don't contemplate it, it can appear that you reject this process of handling the situation and it can get you to really deep and dark places.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, because you turn a blind eye to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all you need to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to, like, figure out guilt before it comes.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just need to recognize that it always remains as a possibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't ignore that possibility of eventual discomfort, pain and resistance to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you learn how to not resist to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: How to endure it and not act out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how it will cease to pressure you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's also how you will not lose perspective when guilt arises.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will see whether it's a rational guilt or irrational guilt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether it's a guilt rooted in something that you genuinely did wrong,
[SPEAKER_00]: Or not rooted in anything you did wrong, but just your own mind winding you up and attacking you.
[SPEAKER_04]: But what happens when you're faced with situations where you can't change the...
I mean, if some people are gone, how can you change the...
[SPEAKER_04]: But you have done wrong in the past.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can stop resisting the guilt here and now.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you free yourself from those actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how Angulimala freed himself from all the murders he committed.
[SPEAKER_00]: He became an arahant here and now.
[SPEAKER_00]: He couldn't change.
[SPEAKER_00]: He couldn't undo his actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he did finally resolve the root of all action, which is craving in regard to feeling, and because of that, none of those actions actually followed him any further.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the only reason you would want to, even theoretically, try and change the past, is because you don't want to endure the present guilt.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, stop resisting the present guilt and past will cease to be a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Could Bhante perhaps share a few more words on how to deal with guilt?
[SPEAKER_01]: How to accept the previous mistakes, paths not taken, wrong paths, etc.?
[SPEAKER_01]: How to stop resisting guilt, if there's time?
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, see, you would... all of those things you would want to do, because you don't want to feel guilt.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you would... how to accept past mistakes, so I don't feel bad today, on account of past mistakes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, your acceptance of past mistakes is fueling your guilt, because of which you want to accept the past mistakes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's a vicious circle.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the only way to do it is to stop... to endure the discomfort first.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just have to endure it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, stop resisting it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stop trying to accept the past.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stop trying to come to terms with it, because all of that is rooted in you still resisting the presently-endured
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you first stop doing everything or anything on account of it and endure it, then you'll see where to go.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then you'll see that within that non-resistance, you can get to look closer at that guilt which is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the only reason it hurts is because you resist it.
[SPEAKER_00]: In itself, it doesn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't cause you pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like a hot burning embers don't hurt unless, you know, you reach out with your hand to grab them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stop reaching out.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how do you stop reaching out?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, by enduring the pain first, to see what causes it directly.
[SPEAKER_00]: The present pain is not caused by things you did in the past, things done to you in the past, things you missed in the past, opportunities you... whatever else you didn't seize and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Present pain is caused by present resistance to a present feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the first noble truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: The root of suffering is not the past.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not the guilt.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not who said what said when they said it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's basically taṇha in regard to what you feel.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: There and then.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you really want to take it in a broader sense, it doesn't really matter what type of feeling there is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether it's a guilt, whether it's a pleasant feeling, the point is, you need to learn how, here and now, not to resist it and not to indulge it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how not to lose perspective in regard to what you feel here and now.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all.
[SPEAKER_00]: Really, just don't forget about yourself in regard to how you're feeling in this present moment.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you sustain that attitude, that's basically the correct practice of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: A perspective being deeply rooted in your gratuitous resistance to a presently enduring feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because feeling is there whether you resist it or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: So until you stop resisting it, it will bother you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe I have a somewhat related question, now that I've been listening to this advice.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was basically how to improve tolerance to pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, certain pains I have no problems with.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if my finger hurts, it's not a big deal.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, for example, pain in the head.
[SPEAKER_01]: I find myself quickly grabbing the pills, because it
[SPEAKER_01]: It's very difficult for me to think clearly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, there are pains in the body where your mind remains intact, and there are pains that make it harder to think.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I'm thinking that this is also probably the reason why my tolerance to pain is so low.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's also very hard to decide and insist upon it when you're not even really able to think, when you're in the
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so you have to decide before that pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have to anticipate it and then decide what to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in this case, you know, if it's like a serious, life-threatening pain that might compromise, you know, your ability in long term, then you address it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if it's just an uncomfortable headache that will prevent you to think for a while and kind of, you know, make you numb, painful and confused, well, really, the reason you're taking the medicine there is not because of the pain in the head, it's because of the fear.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of losing that clarity and levels of management and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, it's a psychological cause.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're afraid of the pain that might sort of interfere with your operation and that scares you and that's why you take the pill.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why you... if it's not, as I said, if it's just a headache, life-threatening pain, not life-threatening pain, you could just decide beforehand to not do it and endure it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And experience that discomfort and confusion and everything else that comes with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no other magical way.
[SPEAKER_00]: What can I do so I don't have to go through it, but get the results of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Tolerance is developed through tolerance.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's really... the important part is to recognize that these feelings... enduring of the feelings will purify you only if you're enduring them on the right level.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you're enduring, like, random feelings and random discomforts of the physical kind, that will not do anything necessarily to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why Buddha said, you know, self-mortification and asceticism is misguided, because people assume that the enduring physical discomforts will somehow lead them, you know, to purification and everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you endure the feelings on the right level, which is that mental level, see, you have to endure now the pressure to act out of fear in regard to your headache that will impede you and complicate your day.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you endure non-action on the level of that fear, that endurance of that feeling will actually contribute towards the purification, will contribute to a strengthening of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you're just enduring the pain in your leg for the sake of a pain in your leg, that's equally pointless.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, as long as you get to learn something from it, then it's valuable?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, as long as you see where it is rooted, whether it's rooted in, sort of, what state of mind is the root of it, and then you endure it on the level of the state of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you start seeing it there, then, see, you realize fear of the headache is the problem, not the headache in itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means you're liable to fear and it can be caused then by other things, not just the headache.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you start enduring that feeling on that level, not acting out of it, not resisting it, you are actually preparing your mind for any type of discomfort and
[SPEAKER_00]: unpleasant confusion and so on, that might arise on account of various circumstances for as long as you live.
[SPEAKER_01]: So far, I haven't realized that this was actually... there was fear behind it, but it makes sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you for this one.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fear or resistance through having to... psychological resistance through having to go through that ordeal?
[SPEAKER_04]: So, Bhante, regarding the right contemplation question.
[SPEAKER_00]: Uh-huh.
I wanted to ask you before, but you already answered me.
I wanted to ask you just practical way how are you dealing with the
[SPEAKER_04]: For example, with the degradation of your physical and mental capacities and so on, but you answer that the right approach is when you are contemplating that.
So, I just have a like a practical question.
What is then the right contemplation of that?
[SPEAKER_03]: How do you approach this question?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, any Buddhist contemplation can only be developed on the basis of already developed virtue and sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, really, if a person is still struggling with restraining their senses and upholding the precepts and sustaining the context of the precepts and avoiding certain types of action and so on and engagements,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what needs to be developed first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because none of these... all of these contemplations will remain abstract if a person has not created the basis of virtue, the aggregate of virtue that I'm going to refer to.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you have created that, well, then it's kind of... it becomes almost self-explanatory.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are already going to be more aware of that, well, yeah, impermanent nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you are not being distracted anymore through acting out of your senses and chasing pleasures and hiding away from pain irrationally and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're already recognizing that you are subjected to things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, all you need to have is a thought of death and you'll be subjected to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you already trained your mind to not turn away, not run away, not act out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the reason why people can't contemplate
[SPEAKER_00]: Death, correctly.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you think it, it just remains abstract, because there is no basis for it to land.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, where it does land, where something does remind you of death, inadvertently, well, you immediately turn away, or try to psychologize it, cover it up, explain it, just so you don't endure it on that unpleasant level.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, through development of virtues and sense restraint, you are basically enabling yourself to endure things on that unpleasant level.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay, but I think that if I think and contemplate it, yes, for the most of what is going on in people's lives, you can come to the one point where you can understand and you accept it and so on.
[SPEAKER_04]: But I think that this subject of that, it's so...
[SPEAKER_04]: How do you say it?
[SPEAKER_04]: Unrecognizable and so big thing that I hope that you come to the one time to the point where you can understand it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are closer to contemplating death when you are practicing sense restraint than you are when you think about death on the basis of non-sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whether you think about death or not, if you keep the virtue, practice sense restraint, don't act towards sensuality, that is already closer to the contemplation of death, contemplation of cessation.
[SPEAKER_00]: And your idea of contemplation, if it's based on the non-restraint, non-virtue, it's not actually that close.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not... it does not stand for that which death is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's why people are so afraid of giving up sensual pleasures.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it feels like dying.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you want to contemplate death?
[SPEAKER_00]: Keep the eight precepts, don't act out of sensuality, endure your mind, and you're gonna have a first-hand experience of fading away.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have a small question about the choices of the words that we use when we talk about contemplation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, what is the difference between contemplation and introspection?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is this, like, the same?
[SPEAKER_01]: Would it mean the same thing or is there a difference to it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: I guess it could mean... depends, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think you just have to explain what you mean by each term and then see if they correspond to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think contemplation would be, I suppose, for me at least, something that's based on some sort of instruction.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, contemplation is an introspection with prior instruction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Introspection can just be introspection with all sorts of instruction or none of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just before I was introduced to Buddhism, I've heard a lot about introspection and very little about contemplation and the terms never connected for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right, right.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, definitely, definitely.
[SPEAKER_00]: Contemplation should be a form of introspection.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's say like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Contemplation should not be just pondering about abstract terms and how they relate in space and time and what the connections are and how they correspond and what are their similarities.
[SPEAKER_00]: Contemplation should be seeing those things introspectively, on the level of... that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: It needs to be taken personally and seen on that personal level.